Guide to the Willy Arnheim papers, 1962-1985 MS2162
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Willy Arnheim papers
1962-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Arnheim, Willy
MS2162
0.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains reports, photographs, slides, correspondence, and clippings related to the restoration of the West Front of the United States Capitol. The material dates from 1962 to 1985. The reports, images, and correspondence deal with the technical issues involved in the restoration, whereas the clippings are mainly concerned with the political debates surrounding the proposed expansion and restoration of the building.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Alaine Arnheim in 1988.
Historical or Biographical Note
Willy Arnheim (1911-1990) was an expert in stone construction techniques, and worked as a consultant for the restoration of several stone buildings in Washington, D.C., including the United States Capitol, Smithsonian Institution, and National Gallery of Art. Arnheim was born in 1911 in Sweden, and immigrated to the United States in 1928. He worked as a stone mason and union organizer before serving as construction superintendent on over 100 buildings in the Washington, D.C. area and around the country. Arnheim died in 1990.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains reports, photographs, slides, correspondence, and clippings related to the restoration of the West Front of the United States Capitol. The material dates from 1962 to 1985. The reports, images, and correspondence deal with the technical issues involved in the restoration, whereas the clippings are mainly concerned with the political debates surrounding the proposed expansion and restoration of the building. Note that in most cases the clippings have been discarded and replaced with lists of the articles' titles, sources, and dates. Some items, namely Preliminary Plans and Estimates of Cost for the Extension of the West Central Front of the Capitol (1967), United States Capitol: Restoration of the West Central Front: Feasibility and Cost Study (January 1971), and United States Capitol: The Restoration of West Central Facade: Preparation of Alternative Designs: Report (March 1978), have been separated from this collection and are now kept in the book collection.
Mall, The (Washington, D.C.); Photographs; United States Capitol (Washington, D.C.); Black-and-white slides; Historic preservation; Color slides; Arnheim, Willy
- West Front clippings, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- West Front--Daily record, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Names, addresses and phone numbers (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Report to Elliott Carroll, 06/20/1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Original charts and sketches, 06/17/1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Color photographs and sketches [Sketches only], 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- U.S. Capitol West Front, 01/09/1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- U.S. Capitol, 01/04/1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ammann and Whitney (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Restoration of Historic Buildings Constructed with Natural Stone", 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- West Front photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
- West Front photographs, 04/19/1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  General note
  Caption: "U.S. Capitol West Front"
- West Front photographs, 04/19/1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- West Front photographs, 05/31/1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- West Front Photographs, 05/31/1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- West Front photographs, 10/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- West Front photographs, 10/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- West Front photographs, 10/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- West Front photographs, 10/11/1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Caption: "Trees at the West Front of the Capitol"
- West Front photographs, 10/11/1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- West Front photographs, 10/11/1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- West Front photographs, 07/31/1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- West Front photographs, 07/31/1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- West Front photographs, 11/05/1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- West Front photographs, 08/01/1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- West Front photographs, 05/08/1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- West Front photographs, 05/08/1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Caption: "West Front -- U.S. Capitol (West Wall of "South Bldg.")"
- West Front photographs, 05/08/1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Caption: "West Front -- U.S. Capitol --with timber shoring"
- West Front photographs, 05/08/1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Caption: "West Front -- U.S. Capitol -- with timber shoring"
- West Front photographs, 05/14/1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Caption: "New 'West Front' shown on plan printed in Nat. Geographic Mag. for May, 1967"
- West Front photographs, 01/12/1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Caption: "View of Mall from West Front of Capitol"
- West Front photographs, 01/12/1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Caption: "View of Penna Ave NW from West Front of Capitol"
- West Front photographs, 01/26/1968 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Caption: "West Front -- U.S. Capitol from H.E.W. Build. roof"
- West Front photographs, 01/26/1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Caption: "West Front -- Line of alignment of Marshall Stane"
- West Front photographs, 01/26/1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Text on photograph: "Justice Marshall is out of line"
- Color slides, 03/1961 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Text on slide: "Mall from West Front"
- Color slides, 03/1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Text on slide: "West Front -- View from Platform"
- Color slides, 01/04/1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Text on slide: "U.S. Capitol--West Front full view"
- Color slides, 01/04/1976 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Text on slides: "U.S. Cap. -- West Front center part"
- Color slides, 01/04/1976 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Text on slide: "U.S.C. West Front 2nd wind. from N. end cent. part"
- Color slides, 01/09/1976 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Text on slide: "U.S. Capitol West Front -- full view"
- Color slides, 01/09/1976 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Text on slide: "U.S. Capitol West Front center part"
- Color slides, 01/09/1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Text on slide: "U.S. Capitol -- West Fr. 2nd wind. cent. part"
- Color slides, 03/08/1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Text on slide: "Bi-Cent. eyesore -- West Front. Wash Star story"
- Color slides, 03/08/1976 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Text on slide: "Glue for West Front Eve. Star story"
- Color slides, 06/11/1967 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Text on slide: "U.S. Capitol West Front"
- Color slides, 08/09/1967 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Text on slide: "West Front fountain"
- Color slides, 08/09/1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Text on slide: "West Front North elev. --of cent."
- Color slides, 08/09/1967 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Text on slide: "West Front model"
- Color slides, 06/01/1980 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Text on slide: "West Front U.S. Capitol"
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  Text on slide: "West Front -- U.S. Capitol"
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Text on slide: "West Fron -- U.S. Capitol"
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Color slides, 06/19/1980 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Bronze doors by Louis Amateis, 1962-1972 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Methods of restoration, 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Correspondence, 04/05/1964-07/31/1972 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Correspondence, 05/04/1983-07/12/1983 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Correspondence, 08/12/1964 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/07/1964 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  Text on photograph: "West Front drilling"
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  Text on photograph: "West Front"
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/07/1967 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 08/07/1964 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  Text on photograph: "Valenti and Ramsburg"
- Correspondence, 10/12/1964 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 10/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  Text on photograph: "West Front North Elev. Basement Fl. Windows"
- Correspondence [associated photographs] (Box 1, Folder 72)
  Text on photograph: "Stewarts Recepts. Office Window"
- Correspondence [associated photographs], 10/06/1964 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  Text on photograph: "West Front -- Portico"
- Mario E. Campioli, 07/01/1968-09/11/1972 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Clippings--Politicians, 1965-1976 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Feasibility Study by Praeger-Kavanaugh-Waterbury, 01/1971 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Statement on P-K-W study by Willy Arnheim (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Praeger-Kavanaugh-Waterbury and Yankee Stadium, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- News reports on engineering studies of West Front, 1966-1981 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- The West Front -- A Critique of Restoration Proposals by Willy Arnheim, 01/1981 (Box 1, Folder 80)